<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | Megan Rafferty</title>
    <link>https://meganrafferty.github.io/tag/projects/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://meganrafferty.github.io/tag/projects/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 02 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://meganrafferty.github.io/media/icon_hu8e6806e14b71a133e34a8902555b6f91_8319_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://meganrafferty.github.io/tag/projects/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mapping Social Vulnerability</title>
      <link>https://meganrafferty.github.io/project/mapping-social-vulnerability/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://meganrafferty.github.io/project/mapping-social-vulnerability/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Social vulnerability refers to a community&amp;rsquo;s resilience when confronted by external stresses on human health. Factors such as poverty and lack of access to transportation may weaken a community&amp;rsquo;s ability to withstand the impacts from adverse events such as natural disasters and public health crises, which can lead to human suffering and financial loss. At the individual level, social vulnerability can also impact one&amp;rsquo;s ability to manage chronic conditions like cancer or diabetes and has been associated with a higher likelihood of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ahajournals.org/doi/10.1161/CIRCOUTCOMES.121.008612&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;in-hospital mortality with COVID-19&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.atsdr.cdc.gov/placeandhealth/svi/fact_sheet/fact_sheet.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;social vulnerability index (SVI)&lt;/a&gt; was created by the Centers for Disease Control &amp;amp; Prevention (CDC) and the Agency for Toxic Substances and Disease Registry (ATSDR) to measure social vulnerability. While initially developed for emergency preparedness, such as how to allocate resources during a crisis, the SVI has since been adopted to risk stratification and healthcare efforts due to the link between SVI and the social determinants of health. In other words, social vulnerability is tied to overall health and wellness and can negatively impact both individuals and their communities, such as leading to higher rates of diseases and healthcare utilization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I created the &amp;ldquo;Mapping Social Vulnerability&amp;rdquo; tool to explore social vulnerability across the United States. The interactive tool can be used to identify communities at higher risk of adverse health outcomes or with greater social and healthcare needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /../assets/media/overall_svi_hu7fba9da1679ce4a56c592454604cb9c1_502955_254153f2ae35bfce3d8cc99df1f59d17.webp 400w,
               /../assets/media/overall_svi_hu7fba9da1679ce4a56c592454604cb9c1_502955_12b73ae0b1df8ca2db93c84934bd9a0e.webp 760w,
               /../assets/media/overall_svi_hu7fba9da1679ce4a56c592454604cb9c1_502955_1200x1200_fit_q100_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://meganrafferty.github.io/../assets/media/overall_svi_hu7fba9da1679ce4a56c592454604cb9c1_502955_254153f2ae35bfce3d8cc99df1f59d17.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;465&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Visualizing Machine Learning</title>
      <link>https://meganrafferty.github.io/project/ml_viz/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://meganrafferty.github.io/project/ml_viz/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I created an interactive dashboard to visualize the effects of imbalanced data and other parameters on model performance metrics. This is part of a larger effort to use visualization to help convey the intuition behind machine learning models and concepts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For ease of accessibility, the dashboard was created in a Jupyter notebook and can be used within the notebook itself or deployed using Python&amp;rsquo;s Voila framework. To learn more about the project, see the GitHub link above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34;
           src=&#34;https://meganrafferty.github.io/../assets/media/viz_demo.gif&#34;
           loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Predicting In-Hospital Mortality for Traumatic Brain Injury</title>
      <link>https://meganrafferty.github.io/project/predicting-mortality-tbi/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://meganrafferty.github.io/project/predicting-mortality-tbi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The following is an overview of an independent project of mine. These findings have not been peer reviewed.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;objective&#34;&gt;Objective&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traumatic Brain Injury (TBI) is a significant health concern that results in disability and death of thousands of people each year in the United States. TBI occurs when a sudden trauma causes damage to the brain and is characterized by a disruption in the normal function of the brain. Symptoms can be mild, moderate, or severe depending on the intensity of damage to the brain tissue. This aim of this analysis was to predict in-hospital mortality in TBI patients with diagnosis of intracranial hemorrhage (ICH), a common and severe feature of severe TBI. Identifying modifiable risk factors and predicting outcomes among ICH patients may be useful in managing prognostic expectations, making treatment decisions, reducing in-hospital mortality, and improving health outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;methods&#34;&gt;Methods&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Statewide hospital trauma registry data from years 2012 to 2016 were obtained and relevant demographic, injury, and clinical variables were selected for this analysis. The dataset was filtered by ICD-9 codes and other clinical variables to identify patients admitted with traumatic brain injury and intracranial hemorrhage. Patients under the age of 20 were excluded. Missing values were imputed or dropped, and relevant variables were transformed (e.g., encoding, scaling) and engineered as necessary. The dataset was then randomly split with a 75:25 ratio into training and test sets, totaling 8,215 and 2,738 observations, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Logistic regression, random forest, and gradient boosting models were investigated. For logistic regression, LASSO was used for feature selection, and cubic splines were used for non-linearly associated continuous predictors. For random forest and boosting, all initially selected variables were included in the models. Hyperperamaters were tuned using stratified 5-fold cross-validation in order to find the optimal values. To assess and compare predictive performance for each model on the test set, accuracy, area under the curve (AUC), sensitivity, and specificity were computed. Receiver Operator Curves (ROC) were constructed to illustrate predictive performance. In addition, model performance was assessed and compared after using a downsampling technique on the training set in an attempt to correct the bias introduced by a class imbalance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;findings&#34;&gt;Findings&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following variable selection, the final model for logistic regression included gender, age, systolic blood pressure, ICU length of stay, primary payment method, Glasgow coma score (GCS), injury severity score (ISS), and concussion. Significant interaction terms between ICU stay and ISS were included. For random forest and boosting models, all initially selected variables were included in the model. The most important predictors were ISS, GCS, and ICU stay based on feature importance scores. Performance metrics for each of the three models are shown below in Table 1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /../assets/media/tbi_table_hu7fba9da1679ce4a56c592454604cb9c1_183418_673cafb6af4a96a62fdf8f8823f8e3d6.webp 400w,
               /../assets/media/tbi_table_hu7fba9da1679ce4a56c592454604cb9c1_183418_ef82ff301e2fb939d066a76182239e2c.webp 760w,
               /../assets/media/tbi_table_hu7fba9da1679ce4a56c592454604cb9c1_183418_1200x1200_fit_q100_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://meganrafferty.github.io/../assets/media/tbi_table_hu7fba9da1679ce4a56c592454604cb9c1_183418_673cafb6af4a96a62fdf8f8823f8e3d6.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;208&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, logistic regression outperformed both random forest and gradient boosting models across both data sets. All models had high predictive performance with the full data set, but logistic regression performed slightly better (AUC = 0.923) compared to gradient boosting (AUC = 0.903) and random forest (AUC = 0.886). However, all models had poor sensitivity (0.41-0.462). Considering the potential clinical application of rapid identification of high-risk patients, high sensitivity of the prediction model may be of greater importance to a clinician.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the downsampled data set, all models saw an increase in AUC and sensitivity and a small decrease in specificity. Logistic regression (AUC = 0.934) once again outperform boosting (AUC = 0.912) and random forest (AUC = 0.914) in terms of AUC. However, the gradient boosting model had the greatest sensitivity (SN = 0.904) among models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /../assets/media/tbi_roc_curves_hu7fba9da1679ce4a56c592454604cb9c1_317018_b3ce90ffaa5bf29e9cbcffd233ff5f5b.webp 400w,
               /../assets/media/tbi_roc_curves_hu7fba9da1679ce4a56c592454604cb9c1_317018_05f5c99899aed2cb5f13b64fa401fb35.webp 760w,
               /../assets/media/tbi_roc_curves_hu7fba9da1679ce4a56c592454604cb9c1_317018_1200x1200_fit_q100_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://meganrafferty.github.io/../assets/media/tbi_roc_curves_hu7fba9da1679ce4a56c592454604cb9c1_317018_b3ce90ffaa5bf29e9cbcffd233ff5f5b.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;305&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;significance&#34;&gt;Significance&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Real-world data, such as those from trauma registries, provide a rich source of data for training predictive and prognostic models and can be used to make real-world impact in healthcare decision making. Early prediction of in-hospital mortality can help clinicians and other healthcare personnel manage prognostic expectations, inform resource management, make treatment decisions in a timely manner, and ensure that patients are receiving appropriate care.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Predictors of Survival among Adrenal Cortical Carcinoma Cases</title>
      <link>https://meganrafferty.github.io/project/predictors-of-survival-acc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://meganrafferty.github.io/project/predictors-of-survival-acc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The following is an overview of an independent research project of mine that I presented at a national conference.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adrenal cortical carcinoma (ACC) is a rare and aggressive cancer with poor prognosis. It is the second most aggressive endocrine cancer following anaplastic thyroid cancer and has an estimated annual incidence of 0.7–2.0 cases/million. Because of the low incidence of these tumors, data on prognostic factors and survival outcomes are limited. The aim of this analysis was to examine demographic, clinical, and tumor characteristics as potential predictors of overall survival using the 1975-2016 Surveillance, Epidemiology, and End Results (SEER) program data set, which encompasses approximately 34.6% of the US population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;methods&#34;&gt;Methods&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reported cases of ACC from 2006 to 2015 were identified, and relevant demographic and clinicopathological data were retrieved, including age at diagnosis, sex, race and ethnicity, tumor laterality, tumor grade, tumor size, clinical summary stage, and surgical treatment. Cases were limited to adults to account for established differences between adult and pediatric ACC patients in incidence, clinical presentation, and biological behaviors. Multivariable Cox proportional hazards regression was utilized to examine the associations between overall survival and demographic and tumor-specific variables. Tree-based survival analysis (TBSA) was used to further elucidate the relationship between potential predictors and mortality risk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While not as widely used as the Cox Proportional Hazards model for survival data, survival trees are useful nonparametric alternatives. Tree-based methods are simple, easily interpreted, and flexible. Similar to other regression tree analyses, TBSA adaptively partitions the study populations into groups that have different survival distributions, helping to identify hierarchical predictive relationships. The method used in this analysis follows a recursive partitioning algorithm that adopts most aspects of the well-known classification and regression tree algorithm. Using the first step of a full likelihood estimation procedure for the splitting criterion, this method is able to obtain tree-structured relative risk estimates for censored survival data. After growing the initial survival tree, cross-validation and a cost-complexity pruning algorithm were utilized to identify the optimally-pruned tree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among ACC cases, the median overall survival time was 21 months, and one- and five-year survival rates were 61% and 32%, respectively. Log-rank tests revealed significant differences in overall survival when stratified by surgery, stage, age, and sex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Age, surgical treatment, and tumor stage were found to be significant prognostic factors for overall survival, with surgical treatment having a dominant effect. Those who did not undergo surgical treatment had 3.24 times the mortality risk compared to those who did. Clinical stage was also an important predictor. Those with localized cancer had significantly lower mortality risk compared to those with regional and distant cancer. Compared to those with localized cancer, those with regional cancer had 2.23 times the mortality risk, while those with distant cancer had 3.09 times the mortality risk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /../assets/media/survival_results_hu92017aae938d77c020bb4c5ca0c93118_559611_25a2650dd6b1f9a3c4719b0cfacbb0c3.webp 400w,
               /../assets/media/survival_results_hu92017aae938d77c020bb4c5ca0c93118_559611_ee3c37df3cdd2abb19f82f9a95dbc6fa.webp 760w,
               /../assets/media/survival_results_hu92017aae938d77c020bb4c5ca0c93118_559611_1200x1200_fit_q100_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://meganrafferty.github.io/../assets/media/survival_results_hu92017aae938d77c020bb4c5ca0c93118_559611_25a2650dd6b1f9a3c4719b0cfacbb0c3.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;430&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results of TBSA corroborated these findings. Sex, age, race and ethnicity, surgical treatment, clinical stage, and tumor size were included in the TBSA modeling. Using the optimal complexity parameter (which controls the trade-off between the subtree’s complexity and its fit to the data) and cross validation to identify the optimally pruned tree, we see here the final subtree consisting of 5 terminal nodes. Only surgery, stage, and age were selected as significant predictors in the model. Surgical treatment (seen as the root node) was found to have the greatest importance in the model, followed by clinical stage, then age. Those who did not undergo surgical had the highest relative mortality rate according to the computed relative risk estimates, which can be seen in the top line of each terminal node. Looking at the farthest terminal node to the right, we can see that those who did not undergo surgical treatment had a relative mortality rate of 3.2 times the overall mortality rate. To find the prognostic group with the lowest relative mortality rate, we start at the root node (surgery) and work our way down the left of the tree. Those who underwent surgery, had localized disease stage, and were &amp;lt;55 years old at time of diagnosis had the lowest relative mortality rate at 0.32 times the overall mortality rate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /../assets/media/survival_results_2_hu92017aae938d77c020bb4c5ca0c93118_329965_8a74b451692e323b036486ce01ca589f.webp 400w,
               /../assets/media/survival_results_2_hu92017aae938d77c020bb4c5ca0c93118_329965_a52b0010d70855346ad17dff0f9ec0cd.webp 760w,
               /../assets/media/survival_results_2_hu92017aae938d77c020bb4c5ca0c93118_329965_1200x1200_fit_q100_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://meganrafferty.github.io/../assets/media/survival_results_2_hu92017aae938d77c020bb4c5ca0c93118_329965_8a74b451692e323b036486ce01ca589f.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;430&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Texas COVID-19 School District Monitoring Dashboard</title>
      <link>https://meganrafferty.github.io/project/covid_dashboard/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://meganrafferty.github.io/project/covid_dashboard/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Texas School District COVID-19 Monitoring Dashboard is a dashboard built by my team at the Texas Policy Lab to help Texas policymakers, school districts, and parents of school-age students make better and more informed decisions about COVID-19 mitigation during the pandemic. The dashboard was developed based on guidance from the Centers for Disease Control (CDC) and tracks several standardized metrics, including case numbers, test positivity rates, and hospital capacity, and transmission risk levels within counties and school districts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /../assets/media/covid_dashboard_hu789af5602b0564dea21bcf1e67237882_633297_1ac736291a193d258e68a04ee1e6c55d.webp 400w,
               /../assets/media/covid_dashboard_hu789af5602b0564dea21bcf1e67237882_633297_7518882515164efe798f299648452b60.webp 760w,
               /../assets/media/covid_dashboard_hu789af5602b0564dea21bcf1e67237882_633297_1200x1200_fit_q100_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://meganrafferty.github.io/../assets/media/covid_dashboard_hu789af5602b0564dea21bcf1e67237882_633297_1ac736291a193d258e68a04ee1e6c55d.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;455&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
